<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A copie of a letter lately sent by a gentleman, student in the lawes of the realme, to a frende of his concernyng. D. Story</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1571</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117854</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853063</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853063</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18427</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13003)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18427)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 318:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A copie of a letter lately sent by a gentleman, student in the lawes of the realme, to a frende of his concernyng. D. Story</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Day?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1571]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: 4. Iunii. 1571.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Story, John, 1510?-1571.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:18427:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18427:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A COPIE OF A LETTER LATELY SENT BY a Gentleman, ſtudent in the lawes of the Realme, to a frende of his concernyng. D. Story.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18427:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:18427:2"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to your requeſt, you ſhal hereby vnderſtand what you may truely ſaye &amp; auowe vpon ſuch queſtions as it ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth you haue harde, of the late execution of .D. Storie, who ſuffred at Tiburne the firſt of Iune laſt.</p>
               <p>It is notorious howe euyll and vnloyally he behaued hym ſelfe here in Englande be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he departed the Realme, and howe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt a perſecutor afterward he was of all the good ſubiectes of Englande, hauyng cauſe to be in the lowe countreys, both before the arreſt made of late by the Duke of Alua, as ſence that tyme a multitude of honeſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes knowe it, both Englyſhe &amp; others, and a great number haue felt it by impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment procured by hym, and by ſeaſyng and confiſcatyng of their goodes, ſo as there is no doubt to be made, but that he was to his power as earneſt an enemie to the ſtate of Englande his naturall countrey, and the Queenes Maieſties good ſubiectes, as any man borne in this Realme coulde be. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, becauſe at the place of his execution before his death, he vſed long &amp; many ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to moue ſome of ſimple vnderſtandyng,
<pb facs="tcp:18427:3"/> or that dyd not knowe his rancor and malice agaynſt the Queenes Maieſtie, and the ſtate of this Realme, and for that it was not then conuenient, nor at leaſt coulde be imagined aforehande that he woulde haue vſed ſuche ſpeeches at that tyme, and ſo he was ſuffred to ſpeake altogether without contradiction, whereby the trueth percaſe may be made to you obſcure, you ſhall vnderſtande of what deteſtable crymes he was gyltie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhoulde haue ben particulerly charged at the tyme of his arraignement in the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Benche, but that he craftyly and trayto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, knowyng by his examination wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was to be charged, and howe much he hym ſelfe had confeſſed in the Towre: and beyng wrytten in certayne leaues of paper had ſubſcribed with his owne hande wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, refuſed to haue any tryall made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, alleaging that he ought not to anſwere, nor would anſwere, becauſe he was ſubiect to the Kyng of Spayne, and not ſubiect to the Queenes Maieſtie &amp; the crowne of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande: and ſo although he was charitably, earneſtly, and reaſonably required at his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment to anſwere to the matters wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was charged by inditement, as a borne ſubiect of this Realme, yet he woulde
<pb facs="tcp:18427:3"/> not, but traytorouſlye refuſed to anſwere thereto, in ſuch ſort, as if he had ben indyted of felonie, as he was of hygh treaſon, he ſhould for his not anſweryng haue ſuffred the payne of preſſyng to death, which maner of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is not vſed in caſes of treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the lawes of the Realme, but was adiudged gyltie of the treaſons conteyned in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement, as of neceſſitie and iuſtice he ought to be, for other iudgement coulde not be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and ſo by iuſtice of lawe he was iudged to the death which he ſuffred. But for that it may ſerue to the ſatiſfaction of all men, to conſyder howe farre he was gyltie of the treaſons conteyned in his indytement, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after foloweth a true, iuſte, and playne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the matters, both wherof he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed and examined, and which alſo he did confeſſe in the Towre.</p>
               <p>He was to be charged that he dyd trayto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly conſpire agaynſt the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, with one Preſtall an Englyſhe man, who was a fugityue, and principall deuiſor of the firſt Treaſon intended by the young Pooles. xi. yeres paſt, and therof was indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and outlawed: and afterwarde of late tyme he practiſed an other great treaſon
<pb facs="tcp:18427:4"/> with certayne perſons, wherof one diſcloſed the ſame to the Duke of Norfolke, who alſo verye duetifullye reuealed the ſame to the Queenes Maieſtie, wherevpon the ſayde Preſtal beyng ſought for to be apprehended, fledde into Scotiande, where alſo he ioyned hym ſelfe with the Englyſhe rebelles, and there attempted ſundry treaſons againſt her Maieſtie, and from thence he fledde into Flaunders. With this maner of Traytor had this. D. Storie a continuall intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to further his treaſons, inſomuche as he ſayde, not long before he came into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, to one that for dueties ſake diſcloſed it, &amp; is redy to proue it, that Preſtall ſhoulde or it were long, be the leader of .xl. thouſand men into Englande, agaynſt that woman whiche toke vpon her to be Queene, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame Story, I woulde to God ſhe were in the bottome of the ſea, with other vile and reprochfull wordes not meete to be reported. With which traytorous ſpeeches he ſhould haue ben charged, yf he woulde haue abyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den tryall accordyng to the lawes of the Realme.</p>
               <p>The ſayde Storie ſayde alſo in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of two perſons of Engliſh byrth, who
<pb facs="tcp:18427:4"/> were redy to haue charged hym therewith, yf he woulde haue ſtande to tryall, that he had written letters to Bruxels, that yf the matters conteyned therein ſhoulde be reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led where he ſhoulde be charged therewith, he ſhoulde be hanged, drawen, &amp; quartered. And immediatly after this ſpeeche he went to Bruxels with Preſtall, where he and Preſtall were rewarded with money: and there Preſtall declared to certayne perſons, redy alſo to haue auowed the ſame, that he had opened his whole purpoſes to .D. Story, whereto .D. Story was ſworne to kepe the ſame ſecrete. But of the thynges intended by Preſtal and Story at that tyme, neyther of them woulde be then knowen, but yet Preſtall affirmed that he had an art to poyſon any body a farre of, beyng not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with them, and that none coulde do it but he. And to ſhew ſome taſte of their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, a gentleman belongyng to Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile, a ſecretarie to the Duke of Alua, tolde an Englyſhe man, redye alſo to auowe the ſame, that. D. Story and Preſtall were about ſuch matters, and ſuch vyle treaſon, as the ſaide partie ſayde that no man coulde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe worſe, and that .D. Story was ſuche a wicked man as could not be found the like,
<pb facs="tcp:18427:5"/> and that he thought veryly they were about murdring of ſome great perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in England.</p>
               <p>The ſayde Story alſo receaued certayne letters from Preſtall out of Scotland, being written in Scottyſhe, whiche are alſo to be ſeene, and myght haue ben ſhewed at the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignement, yf he woulde haue ben tryed: Which letters Story tranſlated into latin, and caryed the ſame to Bruxels, by whiche it was required that meanes ſhould be made to the Duke of Alua, to ſende into Scotland certayne Horſmen, and a number of dagges, to make an entry &amp; inuaſion into Englande with the Scottes, and by the ſame letter Pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtall wrote, that the thyng whiche he tolde D. Story in ſecrete woulde coſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande markes, and that yf the Regent and the foolyſhe boy the young Kyng were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched &amp; dead, the Scottyſhe Queene were a mariage for the beſt man lyuyng. Al which wordes are conteyned in the letter tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by. D. Story.</p>
               <p>The ſayde Story beyng at Bruxels, and receauyng a letter from elde Norton, a very olde Rebell, beyng arryued at Antwerpe, dyd ſollicite certayne of the counſell about
<pb facs="tcp:18427:5"/> the Duke, for money for the reliefe of the ſame Norton and his company, and wrote to hym to comfort hym by expreſſe wordes, that where he and his company were before but worſhipfull, nowe they were an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtate, and had wonne double honor &amp; perpetuall fame for their late enterpriſe in Englande, and that he woulde come ſhortly to geue them their welcome to Antwerpe, and immediatlye he procured that one. D. Saunders, with certayne Englyſhe fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyues harboured in Louain, went to Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe to the Rebelles, and there Saunders made to them a ſolemne long oration in prayſe of their actes.</p>
               <p>Story alſo declared in Antwerpe in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of ſuch as ſhould haue auowed it at his arraignement yf he woulde haue denyed it, that the Rebellion ſhoulde be renewed in Englande, and that at the ſame inſtant alſo Irelande ſhoulde rebell, whereof he ſayde he was well aſſured by aduertiſement from an Iryſhe biſhop that hadde ſcaped out of the Towre of London, and that at the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant alſo the Scottes ſhoulde with an ayde out of Fraunce inuade Englande, and ſet vp the Scottyſhe Queene.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18427:6"/>
               <p>The ſayde Story alſo vſed commonly this maner of prayer after his meates, whereof there are diuers perſons redy to witnes the ſame that haue hearde hym, and laſtly euen in the Roy wherein he was before he came laſt into Englande, in the preſence of diuers perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that yf the Queenes Maieſtie, whom he woulde neuer tearme but by the name of dame Elzabeth that tooke vppon her to be Queene, woulde not ſpeedylye turne to Queene Maries religion, he prayed that ſhe myght be ouercome with ſworde and fyre, and all that woulde take her part.</p>
               <p>And though he myght haue ben charged with ſundry other traytorous and haynous conſpiracies in the lowe countreys, &amp; with aydyng of the Rebelles there, whereof out of the ſaide lowe countreys aduertiſement was geuen by ſundry of good credite: yet of ſet purpoſe no more is aboue recited, but ſuche thynges only as wherwith he ſhoulde haue ben charged openly by witneſſes at his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignement, who yf he woulde haue denyed the ſame, ſhoulde haue auowed the whole to his face, and in the hearyng of the Iury that ſhoulde haue tryed hym. And howe many of the thynges before recited are to be iudged
<pb facs="tcp:18427:6"/> true &amp; probable, it is to ſee by theſe thynges folowyng, whiche are worde by worde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted out of his owne confeſſions, ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with his owne hande, and vttered vpon interrogatories, without any maner of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or offer of torture, although at the place of execution he vſed ſpeeche to the contrary very vntruly, as the worſhipful perſons that examined hym can well teſtifie, which were,</p>
               <p>Sir Thomas Wroth knight, Maiſter Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham then Recorder of London, &amp; Maiſter Peter Oſborne the Treſorers remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer in the Exchequer, &amp; ſo can alſo the Lieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunt of the Towre, as touchyng any tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <head>Extracted out of. D. Stories confeſsions.</head>
               <div type="item">
                  <head>ix. December. 1570.</head>
                  <p>IOhn Story the day and yere aboue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten being examined, ſaith that Iohn Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall dyd wryte a letter to the ſayde Iohn Story, of three ſydes of a ſheete of paper as he remembreth, and directed to the ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:18427:7"/> Story: which letter was incloſed in a letter wrytten to one Hamelton a Scot that lay at Bruxels, for hym to peruſe &amp; ſeale the ſame, and then to delyuer it to the ſayd Story. And the ſame letter the ſayde Hamelton read, and ſealed it vp, and told this examinat the effect therof, and he bad hym open it, and reade it, and ſo the ſayde Hamelton dyd, vntyll he came to a word, Boy or chylde, meanyng the King of Scottes to be made away as the ſaid Story tooke it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="item">
                  <head>xii. December. 1570.</head>
                  <p>Item, he ſayth that Hamelton tolde hym that Preſtall had written, that the matter which Preſtall had tolde Story and the ſayd Hamelton that an Englyſhe man nowe in Irelande could do, would not be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a great ſumme of money, whiche matter was to make the Kyng of Scottes away: for Preſtall had told this examinat and Hamel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, that the Scottes woulde hardlye be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to obedience as long as the Queene of Scottes was without an huſbande, and no man of eſtimation woulde haue her ſo long as the Boy lyued, and yf he were dead, he hoped the Emperours brother woulde haue
<pb facs="tcp:18427:7"/> her, and wyſhed he myght be an entreater in that matter. And further Preſtall ſaid, that the ſaid man nowe in Irelande had tolde the Pooles and hym the very month, the daye, and houre, that the Queene of Englande ſhoulde be in hazarde of her lyfe, and that the ſame Engliſhe man could diſpatch the King of Scottes for money: And beyng aſked what the ſame Englyſhe mans name was, Story ſayth of trouth he knoweth not, but hath forgotten it, yet Preſtal told it him: but whither he is in Irelande, or of what eſtate, degree, or condition he is of, he knoweth not. And further that Preſtall tolde him he coulde do much with that Englyſhe man in Irelande, wherein this examinat diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged hym. And the ſayde Story ſayth he thynketh of his conſcience that Preſtall would do all the harme that he coulde to this Realme of Englande.</p>
                  <p>And further ſayth, that Preſtall tolde hym he woulde take any thyng in hand to inuade Englande, ſo he might haue good aſſiſtance, and not be vſed as an vnderlyng. But Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall neuer tolde hym by what deuice Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande ſhoulde be inuaded.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18427:8"/>
                  <p>And more he ſayth, that Ienny and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenfelde hath made ſuite to Courteuile and to Northcarne, as Northcarnes ſecretarie tolde hym, for the reliefe of the Nortons and Neuyls: and after this Courteuile called this examinat, wyllyng hym to byd Markenfeld to come to hym that day at two of the clocke, and then this examinat prayed that yf he ſhoulde come about the money for the reliefe of the Nortons, and others, that then one Parkar myght be payed for theyr charges, and ſo it myght be delyuered to Parkar.</p>
                  <p>He ſayth he wrote a letter to the elder Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton from Bruxels, and ſhewed the ſayde el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Norton, that he woulde be glad to do for hym euen the beſt that lay in the ſayde Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries power to do, and that he woulde rather ſtay his owne ſuites to the Duke, then not to do the beſt he could for hym, and this was all the effecte of his letter to the ſayde eldeſt Norton: but afterwarde he called to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance he wrote vnto him, that he was glad that he and his company were ſo well come into the catholyke Realme, &amp; ſafely arryued there. He ſayth he doth not remember that he wrote to the ſayde Nortons and the reſte,
<pb facs="tcp:18427:8"/> that where they were before but worſhipful, they were nowe worthy double honor: but he ſayth it may be he dyd write ſo, becauſe he thought ſo: and thynkes he dyd wryte vnto them that he woulde come ſhortly to Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe, &amp; geue them their welcome, becauſe he meant ſo to do.</p>
                  <p>After Markenfelde and Ienny came ouer, &amp; one Leedes with hym, and firſt they came to Parkers houſe, where the ſayde Ienny declared openly at the boorde, in the preſence of this examinat and others, the order of the ſayde late Rebellion.</p>
                  <p>And hereupon this examinat made reporte to Northcarnes ſecretarie, that the ſayde Ienny was a frende to the Catholykes and the Earles, and is a very truſty frende, and hath ventured his lyfe for the Catholykes. But afterwarde this examinat perceauyng the contrary of Ienny by a Scotte, he gaue Northcarnes ſecretarie warnyng to take heede of Ienny.</p>
                  <p>Shortly after this, the ſayde Story came to Antwerpe to Parkars houſe, where ſyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng at dynner, the ſayde elder Norton and
<pb facs="tcp:18427:9"/> ſome other of his company came in from the Churche, and one ſaide, this is Norton, and thereupon this examinat roſe and gaue hym place, and bad him welcome: and ſo the elder Norton ſate downe in the ſaid Stories place.</p>
                  <p>After olde Norton ſhyfted his lodging, and this examinat, with one Shawe Nortons ſonne in lawe, went to the ſayde olde Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons lodging to dyner, and there dined with hym, and that day all their talke was of the ſuſpition that Norton had of Iennys firſte commyng to the Rebelles in Englande from the Earle of Suſſex, and ſo he tooke hym ſtyl but a ſpye, and to couer hym ſelfe with to the Duke, with labouryng for them.</p>
                  <p>He ſayth that he hearde by Markenfeldes report, that the ſayde Nortons and Neuyls &amp; their company, had two hundred crownes geuen them from the Duke at their firſte commyng, and ſhoulde haue two hundred crownes more afterwarde.</p>
                  <p>More he ſayth, that before the Dukes laſt commyng to Antwerpe, the ſaide Story and Sir Iames Shelley beyng at Louain, were there ſent for to come to. D. Saunders to
<pb facs="tcp:18427:9"/> heare a certayne booke read, of the reaſons that the Bull late ſent ouer into Englande ſhould be obeyed as he ſuſpected, and thither the ſayde Story promiſed to come: but that after noone he was dryuen to go to Bruxels, and ſo ſir Iames Shelley went thyther, and brought worde to this examinat being with one Leedes at dyner, that yf he had come, he ſhoulde haue hearde goodly reaſons that he would haue wel lyked, about the booke that Saunders had made.</p>
                  <p>Further the ſayde Story doth ſay, that he was neuer ſworne to King Philip, nor to the Duke of Alua, nor neuer by any meanes was made kyng Philippes ſubiecte or deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, or otherwyſe naturalized to be Kyng Philippes ſubiect, but remaynes only ſtyll a ſubiect to the Queene of Englande.</p>
                  <closer>Thus ſubſcribed, though he ſayd otherwyſe at Tyborne. <signed>Iohn Story.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="item">
                  <head>xx. December. 1570.</head>
                  <p>The ſayde Iohn Story this .xx. day of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember beyng examined, ſayth that about two yeres ſence, he dyd deale by wrytyng
<pb facs="tcp:18427:10"/> with Courteuſle, ſhewyng vnto hym that the Catholykes in Englande dyd dayly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, and the Sciſmatykes dyd there daylye encreaſe, and therfore yf the King of Spayne had any meanyng to wryte to the Queene of Englande, or otherwiſe to helpe to reſtore religion in Englande, he ſhoulde do it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme, or els it woulde be to late: and eyther he dyd wryte further, or ſayde by mouth to the ſayde Courteuile, that yf the Kyng of Spayne dyd but come into the low countrey out of Spayne with a number of ſhyppes, the Catholykes of Englande would thynke as this examinat thought, that he were come to reſtore religion, and would take the Kyng of Spaynes part. And the ſaid Story confeſſeth that he wrote to Courteuile, that if about the realme of England there might go a number of ſhyppes, as men went about Ierico, then the Catholykes of Englande woulde take courage to prepare entry for them that went ſo about with the ſaid ſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. To which ende of entry, by the Kyng of Spaynes power into Englande, the ſaide Story dyd write to Courteuile many tymes by his letters and perſwaſions therein, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng therby that either the King of Spayne woulde write to the Queene of Englande to
<pb facs="tcp:18427:10"/> reſtore the Catholyke religion, or els would make ſome entry into England, &amp; refourme religion, according as he was bounde by his title of Catholyke Kyng, as the ſayde Story thought.</p>
                  <p>Further the ſayde Story ſayth, that Iohn Preſtall at ſuch tyme as he talked with Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melton and this examinat about the death of the Kyng of Scottes as is aforeſayde, when Preſtall had tolde hym as aforeſayde, that the Englyſhe man that fledde into Irelande had tolde the ſayde Preſtall, of the tyme and houre the Queenes Maieſtie ſhould be in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll of her death as is aforeſayde, then Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall ſayde, that yf the ſayde Englyſhe man in Irelande myght be plyed, he could bryng the Queenes hyghnes to death in deede, and ſayde he thought ſurely he coulde do it, and then this examinat ſayd that was to be done by Necromancie.</p>
                  <closer>Subſcribed <signed>Iohn Story.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>It is here to be conſydered alſo howe lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is that the thynges whiche he ſpake at Tiborne for his purgation were true, when at the ſame tyme he woulde haue had by his
<pb facs="tcp:18427:11"/> earneſt ſpeeches then vſed, all the hearers beleue that he vſed neuer any crueltie in Queene Maries time againſt any that were then burnt for religion: but as he ſayde, he dyd but only chyde them, and that he was no cauſe of the death of any, but that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes dyd procure the ſentences of death. And howe vntrue this ſpeeche of his was in that behalfe as to excuſe hym ſelfe, a number of witneſſes lyuyng that manifeſtly ſaw his extreme cruelties, and ſome that felt thereof are very plenteous. And what his hart was towards the Queenes Maieſtie, may playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare by his traytorous wordes in the parliament houſe, where he ſayde, that yf his counſel had ben folowed, the root ſhould haue ben ſtryken downe, and not the braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
               <p>And howe horrible, traytorous, and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous a meanyng he had to refuſe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere at his arraignement, by refuſyng his naturall allegeaunce to the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and this crowne, from which no lawe in the worlde coulde ſeparate hym, &amp; by auow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng that he was a ſubiecte to the Kyng of Spayne, it may appeare in that he ſayde at his arraignement for defence of his trayto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb facs="tcp:18427:11"/> refuſall of his obedience: That Kinges were choſen at the firſt by the people for their neceſſitie, &amp; not the people for their kynges: and therfore the people myght leaue their kynges when they hadde no more neede of them. And ſo the concluſion in his opinion ſerued for hym that he myght refuſe his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall liege lady and Queene. And ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently by that monſtruous reaſon, all kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges may be depriued of their ſubiectes, or of as many as woulde enter into that trayto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous &amp; monſtruous error, at their pleaſure. A thyng of it ſelfe worthy of ſome monſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous death, accordyng to the monſtruouſnes of the treaſon.</p>
               <p>Otherwyſe to remember the vnworthynes of this. D. for his long lewde lyfe in all tymes paſt, is not conuenient, becauſe he is dead, of whom alſo nothyng ſhould be now in this ſort written, but that by his craftye traytorous doynges at his arraignement, and by his vntruethes vttered at his death, trueth it ſelfe ſhoulde take harme, by miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng &amp; miſreportyng: and only in fauour of trueth haue I collected the premiſſes, &amp; for no other purpoſe, &amp; ſo I pray you vſe it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng as you ſhal thynke meete. For al thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:18427:12"/> thynges which are before recited, are many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly to be proued, partly by the very wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges extant, and in no worde altered, and the reſt by ſufficient witneſſes, whereof I haue hadde good regarde euen for truethes ſake, knowyng that almyghtie God is the auenger of all vntrueth.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>4. Iunii. 1571.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18427:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
